宇宙大探索
第五集
宇宙的年龄和体积
The age and size of the cosmos
由光来书写
are written in light.
迷人的本质和恒星的物质
The nature of beauty and the substance of the stars,
时空的定律
the laws of space and time...
原本就存在
they were there all along,
但我们过去未能发现
but we never saw them...
直到我们拥有了更为强大的观察方式
until we devised a more powerful way of seeing.
这种觉醒的故事有很多的开始
The story of this awakening has many beginnings
却不会终止
and no ending.
从不同时间和地方涌现出许多的英雄
Its heroes come from many times and places--
中国古代的哲人
an Ancient Chinese philosopher,
令11世纪伊拉克穆斯林统治者叹服的奇才
a wizard who amazed the caliphs of 11th-century Iraq,
被苛刻奴役的德国可怜孤儿
a poor German orphan enslaved to a harsh master.
每一位都带领我们前进一小步
Each one brought us a little closer
在解开光线之谜的道路上
to unlocking the secrets hidden in light.
大多数的名字都已经被遗忘了
Most of their names are forever lost to us,
但在某处  很久前  某人的匆匆一瞥
but somewhere, long ago, someone glanced up
注意到了光线展示出的神奇
to see light perform one of its magic tricks.
谁知道呢
Who knows?
或许光线的偶然作为
Maybe that quirk of light
为第一位艺术家带来了灵感
inspired the very first artist.
这些都是怎么来的
Where did all this come from?
我们是如何从小量聚居的
How did we evolve from small wandering bands
采集者和猎人 进化而来的
of hunters and gatherers living beneath the stars
最后还成为世界文明的缔造者
to become the builders of a global civilization?
中间的过程是怎样的
How did we get from there to here?
没有统一的答案
There's no one answer.
气候的变化  学会控制火
Climate change, the domestication of fire,
工具的发明 语言发明 农业发展
the invention of tools,  language, agriculture
都有各自的功劳
all played a role.
或许还有其它的
Maybe there was something else, too.
中国  2000多年前
In China, more than 2,000 years ago,
一位名叫 墨子 的哲人 据说发现了
a philosopher named Mo Tze is said to have observed
光线可以在密闭的宝库中
that light could be made to paint a picture
即小孔成像
产生图像
inside a locked treasure room.
这描述的就是第一台照相机
This was the description of the first camera...
暗箱
the camera obscura,
所有成像照相机的原型
the prototype of all image-forming cameras,
包括给你带来图像的这台摄像机
including the one that's bringing you this picture.
利用光线这种有趣的现象
Taking advantage of this funny thing that light does
催生了首部的电影
resulted in what could be called the first movie.
墨子 光线大师  专治各种黑暗
Mo Tze, master of light, worked against all forms of darkness.
军事天才
A military genius
以智抑暴
who only used his talents to prevent violence,
他最著名的成就是
he was legendary for traveling
穿行于战乱的国家间
among the kingdoms of the warring states,
运用巧妙地策略
employing ingenious strategies
劝导各方休战
to talk kings out of going to war.
他是兼爱的倡导者
He was one of the first to dream of universal love
提倡消灭统治者带给人们的
and an end to poverty and other forms of inequality;
贫困与不公
of government for the people...
批判对于宗教和权威的盲从
and to argue against blind obedience to ritual and authority.
在他的著作中  你能发现
In his writings, you can find
科学探索的早期萌芽
early stirrings of the scientific approach.
到墨子那个年代  中国人已经开始
By Mo Tze's time, the Chinese had already been recording
用书籍记录他们的思想 至少上千年了
their thoughts in books for at least a thousand years.
但我们对他的了解 依然仅是只字词组
Still, our knowledge of him is only fragmentary.
通过许多由他和他的追随者
It consists largely of the collection of essays
所著的文集而来
attributed to him and his disciples.
其中一篇 题为《非命》
In one of them, entitled "Against Fate,"
故言必有三表
立论一定要有三项标准
a three-pronged test for every doctrine is proposed.
推究来历
Question its basis--
一、有本之者
是否可以由
ask if it can be verified
普通人的观感再次验证的
...by the sights and senses of common people.
二、有原之者
是否可以推广
ask how it is to be applied
三、有用之者
并使大多数人受益
and if it will benefit the greatest number.
墨子的思想流传很广
Mo Tze was extremely popular,
但他身后的数百年
but a few hundred years after his death,
秦始皇  第一位皇帝
Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor,
统一了中国  独揽大权
and unifier of China, took power.
他将一片大陆变成了一个国家
He took a continent and turned it into a nation
这个现在依然受他影响的国度  中国
that now bears his name... China.
我们大多数人对他的了解大多数是
Most of us know Emperor Qin for the army of 7,000
来自守卫陵墓的7000件兵马俑
terra cotta warriors that guard his tomb.
在秦始皇的领导下
In Emperor Qin's drive
为了巩固辽阔的帝国
to consolidate his far-flung empire,
他采取极端的手段
he took drastic measures
为所有事物都建立了标准
to standardize everything within it.
包括 铸造单一货币
This included mandating a single coinage,
统一度量衡
making uniform all weights and measures,
车辆与道路的宽度  还有
the widths of carts and roads, as well as the precise way
车同轨
中文书写形式的规范
the Chinese language was to be written,
书同文
也包括了什么是可以写 什么是可以想的
including what you were allowed to write and think.
秦始皇以严刑峻罚来控制臣民思想
使臣民不敢反抗 从而达到顺利推行政
秦始皇的哲学 唯一他认可的
Emperor Qin's philosophy-- the only one permitted--
即法家
称之 守法主义
was called "legalism,"
就如同它的字面意思
which is just what it sounded like,
遵纪守法 否则就...
do as the law says... or else.
这种哲学理论对于质疑权威
It's a philosophy that's not highly conducive
不是十分有利
to questioning authority.
百家思想的书籍
...that all the books of the hundred schools of thought
统统烧掉
shall be be burned,
以古讽今者
that anyone who uses history to criticize the present
全家处斩
shall have his family executed.
墨子和孔子的著作
The works of MoTze and Confucius
还有其它哲人的作品
and other philosophers were destroyed
尽毁于世界历史上首次的焚书
in the world's first book burning.
数百名书生英勇抵抗
Hundreds of scholars bravely resisted
试图保护这些禁书
by trying to preserve the forbidden books.
在首都将他们活埋
They were buried alive in the capitol.
咸阳的"焚书坑儒"
科学需要有自由的表达才能繁荣发展
Science needs the light of free expression to flourish.
需要无畏的质疑权威
It depends on the fearless questioning of authority,
开放的交流思想
the open exchange of ideas.
墨子和他的追随者们所记载的
Sparks of curiosity in the writings of Mo Tze
突发奇想都被抹杀了
and his disciples were effectively stomped out.
影片的再次出现 已是另一个千年之后
It would be another thousand years before the next movie.
幸运的是 我们的想象之舟
Luckily, our Ship of the Imagination
可以带我们去任何的空间和时间
can take us anywhere in space... and time.
中国和希腊的古人发现
The ancient Chinese and Greeks observed
光线可以展现出各种神奇
that light could be made
但是却没人去问
to do wonderful things-- but no one asked that question
小孩子和天才们喜欢问的问题  为什么
favored by small children and geniuses alike. Why?
直到一千年前
Until a thousand years ago...
伊拉克的巴斯拉城
In the city of Basra, Iraq,
生活着另一位光线大师
there lived another master of light.
海桑极度渴望了解自然
Ibn al-Hazen had a passionate desire to understand nature.
他对一切都有疑问
He questioned everything,
特别是那些别人认为理所应当的事情
especially those things that everyone else took for granted.
我们怎么能看到  他问
"How do we see?" he asked.
有些在他之前的伟大权威
Some of the great authorities who came before him
认为光线从我们的眼中出发
had taught that rays come out of our eyes and travel
在物体上反射 然后返回我们的眼中
to the objects we see before returning to our eyes.
但海桑不认同 理由是恒星离我们那么远
But al-Hazen reasoned that the stars were too far distant
什么东西可以从我们眼中射向星星
for something in our eyes to travel all the way to them
并在一眨眼的时间内返回
and back in the blink of an eye.
很有道理  但海桑并未止步
Excellent reasoning, but al-Hazen didn't stop there.
他绞尽脑汁探索大自然的奥秘
He searched for ways to compel nature to divulge her secrets.
当时他的文化对于新的见解与质疑是开放的态度
His culture was open to new ideas and questioning.
那是科学发展的黄金时代
It was the golden age of science
在伊斯兰世界
in the Islamic world.
伊斯兰世界从西班牙的科索瓦
One that stretched from Cordoba in Spain
一直延伸到中亚的撒马尔罕
all the way to Samarkand in Central Asia.
基督教和犹太教的学者被敬为上宾
Christian and Jewish scholars were honored guests
在开罗  巴格达的研究机构
at the research institutes of Baghdad, Cairo,
和其它伊斯兰世界的中心
and other Islamic capitols.
不同于秦始皇  哈里发们派遣使者
Instead of burning books, the caliphs sent emissaries
哈里发是穆斯林统治者的称号
在世界各地搜集书籍
around the world in search of books.
哈里发们大量的资助将这些书籍
The caliphs lavishly funded projects to translate, study,
翻译 研究  并保存  流传后世
and preserve them for future generations.
多亏了他们的努力  许多古希腊科学家的
Much of the light of Ancient Greek science would have been
成果才得以保存
permanently extinguished without their efforts.
对科学的狂热在欧洲再次兴起
The reawakening to science that took place in Europe,
发生在几百年后 多亏了伊斯兰学者和
hundreds of years later, was kindled by a flame
科学家对这些文献的
that had been long tended
精心呵护
by Islamic scholars and scientists.
阿拉伯人将新思想由印度传入西方
The Arabs also imported ideas from India to the West,
包括所谓的  阿拉伯数字
including the so-called Arabic numerals
我们至今都在使用
that we all use today,
还有数字0
and the concept of zero...
确实很方便
which comes in handy
特别是当你书写 几十亿又几十亿时
when you want to write "billions and billions."
阿拉伯天文学十分具有影响力
Arabic astronomy was so influential,
我们至今依然用阿拉伯语名字来称呼
that we still call most of the bright stars
那些明亮的恒星
by their Arabic names.
代数  算法  炼金术  酒精 这些英语单词中的 al
And the "al's" in algebra, algorithm, alchemy, and alcohol
证明了阿拉伯语
are just some of the traces left
是科学界的通用语言
from the time when Arabic was the language of science.
11世纪时  海桑准备尝试
In the 11th century, Ibn al-Hazen set about trying
验证他关于光和我们如何看见的理论
to test his ideas about light and how we see.
我们设计了一套实验测定光线如何移动
So we devised an experiment to determine how light moves.
我们在烈日下支起一顶帐篷
We erected a tent in full daylight
将它完全密封 只允许一束光穿过
and sealed it tightly so that only a single ray of light
射入内部的黑暗中
could pierce its inner darkness.
他用他的智慧
With little more than his brains
加上一件笔直的木质工具  尺子
and a straight piece of wood-- a ruler--
海桑完成了一次科学历史上
al-Hazen had accomplished a great leap forward
伟大的跨越
in the history of science.
他发现光线呈直线运动
He discovered that light moves in straight lines.
这只是开始
But he was just getting started.
海桑总结出成像的关键
Al-Hazen figured out that the key to forming any image--
不论 眼睛还是照相机暗箱
whether you're talking about an eye or camera obscura--
都是通过控制光线进入
is a small opening to restrict the light that can enter
黑暗内室的小孔
an otherwise darkened chamber.
光圈将我们周遭繁杂无关的
That aperture excludes the chaos
光线排除在外
of extraneous light rays that surround us.
光圈越小
The smaller the aperture,
进入的光线角度范围越小
the fewer directions that light can come from.
使图像更清晰
And that makes the image sharper.
从而不至于让光线致盲
So instead of being blinded by the light,
我们可以分辨光线呈现的图像
we can see everything it has to show us.
海桑亲自做出了他的暗箱
Al-Hazen made his own camera obscura
令哈里发们赞叹不已
and dazzled the caliphs.
有效的暗箱需要明亮的光线
A camera obscura works best in bright light.
夜空中的星光对它来说太暗淡了
The stars of the night sky are way too dim for this.
我们需要更大的孔来收集光线
We somehow need a bigger opening to collect light,
同时我们需要保持焦点
but we also need to maintain focus.
望远镜从视野的
A telescope collects light
各个角度收集光线
from any spot in its field of view
遍布整个镜片或者镜子
across the entire lens or mirror,
开孔要比照相机暗箱的小孔大许多
an opening much larger than the camera obscura hole.
这是最早的望远镜之一
This is one of the first telescopes...
伽利略在1609年使用过的那个
the one that Galileo looked through in 1609.
他用这个掀开了黑夜的厚重幕布
With it, he pulled aside the heavy curtain of night
并且开始发现宇宙
and began to discover the cosmos.
都归功于镜片
The lens made it possible
镜片为望远镜提供了比我们眼睛
for a telescope to have a much larger light-collecting area
更大的光线收集区域
than our eyes have.
大桶比小桶可以收集更多的雨水
Big buckets catch more rain than small ones.
现代的望远镜拥有更大收集区域
Modern telescopes have larger collecting areas,
高度敏感的探测器
highly sensitive detectors,
并可以长时间锁定同一目标
and they track the same object for hours at a time
以搜集尽可能多的光线
to accumulate as much of its light as possible.
像哈勃 这样的太空望远镜
Space-based telescopes such as the Hubble,
搜集来自最久远星系的
have captured light from the most distant
光线
and ancient galaxies,
为我们带来大量的更清晰的宇宙图片
giving us vastly clearer pictures of the cosmos.
海桑发现了光线成像的原理
Al-Hazen discovered how images are formed by light,
但这并不是他最最伟大的成就
but that was far from his greatest achievement.
他是有史以来设定
Ibn al-Hazen was the first person ever
科学原则的第一人
to set down the rules of science.
他创造了一套纠错机制
He created an error-correcting mechanism,
一套系统的 严格的
a systematic and relentless way
审查错误观念的机制
to sift out misconceptions in our thinking.
探究真相是困难的
Finding truth is difficult...
探究真相的道路是崎岖的
and the road to it is rough.
作为追寻真相的人
As seekers after truth,
不轻易下判断 不轻信古人所云
you will be wise to withhold judgment and not simply put
是十分明智的
your trust in the writings of the ancients.
你必须质疑并且谨慎的验证这些理论
You must question and critically examine those writings
从各个角度
from every side.
你只能接受论据和实验的结果
You must submit only to argument and experiment
而不是别人的说法
and not to the sayings of any person.
因为每个人都有弱点
For every human being is vulnerable
没有人是完美的
to all kinds of imperfection.
作为寻求真相的人
As seekers after truth,
我们必须怀疑并质疑
we must also suspect and question
我们自己的理论  反复论证
our own ideas as we perform our investigations,
避免陷入偏见与疏忽
to avoid falling into prejudice or careless thinking.
接受这些方针  真相就在眼前
Take this course, and truth will be revealed to you.
这就是科学的方式
This is the method of science.
得益于此 我们的机器人大使可以
So powerful that it's carried our robotic emissaries
航行到太阳系的边缘乃至无限的宇宙
to the edge of the solar system and beyond.
它扩展了我们的生命长度
It has doubled our lifespan,
将过去的失落世界
made the lost worlds of the past
带回现在
come alive.
科学使我们可以对遥远的未来
Science has enabled us to predict events
做出预测
in the distant future...
让我们可以彼此以光速交流
and to communicate with each other at the speed of light,
就像你我之间  此时此刻
as I am with you, right at this moment.
这种思考的方式带给我们力量
This way of thinking has given us powers
那种海桑都认为神奇的力量
that al-Hazen himself would have regarded as wizardry.
他将我们带上这条崎岖 无尽的道路
But it was he who put us on this rough, endless road.
将我们带到一个地方
And now it has taken us to a place
在那里即使光线也被黑暗掩盖
where even light itself is enshrouded in darkness.
光线有着独一无二的属性
Light has properties unlike anything else
以人类存在的领域来说
in the realm of human existence.
比如光的速度
Take the speed of light.
光的基础微粒  光子
The basic particle of light, the photon,
当它从原子或分子中诞生时
is born traveling at the speed of light
就有光的速度
as it emerges from an atom or a molecule.
也只有这一种速度
A photon never knows any other speed,
我们尚未发现其它任何可以立即
and we've not found another phenomenon that accelerates
从0加速到速度极限的现象
from zero to top speed instantaneously.
没有别的东西可以移动这么快
Nothing else could move as fast.
当我们尝试将其它粒子不断加速
When we try to accelerate other particles closer and closer
越接近光速  阻力越大
to the speed of light, they resist more and more,
并且越来越重
as though they're getting heavier and heavier.
还没有任何实验可以
No experiment yet devised
将粒子将速度到光的速度
has ever made a particle move as fast as light.
哪是什么
What was that?
你听了吗
You hear something?
说到哪了 哦 对了
Where was I? Oh, yeah.
没有什么可以像光那样
I don't know anything else in life that behaves like light.
我无法将它这种与众不同的属性
I cannot reconcile its strange properties
与我其它的感官相调谐
with everything else my senses tell me.
我们相信我们的感官胜过
Our urge to trust our senses overpowers
测量仪器对于
what our measuring devices tell us about
实际情况的结果
the actual nature of reality.
我们的感官对于普通尺寸物体的普通速度来说
Our senses work fine for life-size objects
没有问题
moving at mammal speeds,
但是却不适用于光速那些神奇的规则
but are ill-adapted for the wonderland laws of lightspeed.
我们甚至不明白为什么会有宇宙速度极限
We don't even know why there's a cosmic speed limit.
时间在达到光速时静止
Time stands still when you're traveling at the speed of light.
到底什么是光
What is light, anyway?
艾萨克・牛顿始终对光非常着迷
Isaac Newton's enduring fascination with light
从他还是个孩子时
began when he was a child...
就在这个房子里
in this very house.
他在弱冠之年  就是第一位
By the time he was in his 20s, Newton became the first person
破译彩虹奥秘的人
to decipher the mystery of the rainbow.
牛顿发现有些光  白光
Newton discovered that some light, or white light,
由所有彩虹的颜色混合而成
is a mixture of all the colors of the rainbow.
重大的发现
Major discovery.
他将之称为 光谱
He named the displays of colors a "spectrum"
来源于拉丁语中的幻影 或者幽灵
from the Latin for "phantom" or "apparition."
牛大师 抱歉打扰了
Begging your pardon, Master Newton,
晚饭再不吃就要坏了
the cook frets that your dinner will spoil, sir.
呀麦蝶 小牛 别把放大镜放下
No, Isaac, don't put the magnifying glass down!
光里还有更神奇的东西
Something even more amazing is hidden in the light--
一串密码  一条通向宇宙的钥匙
a code, a key to the cosmos.
牛顿错过了很重要的一项发现
Isaac Newton didn't miss much, but that one was a beaut.
他错过了那扇通向神秘宇宙的门
He just walked right past the door to a hidden universe;
那扇门直到150年后才再次开启
a door that would not swing open again for another 150 years.
归功于另一位科学家
It would fall on another scientist,
1800年 在工作时
working in the year 1800,
无意间发现了
to stumble on a piece of evidence
我们周围无可见世界的证据
for the unseen worlds that surround us.
晚上  威廉・赫歇尔搜索天空
By night, William Herschel scanned the heavens
使用当时最大的望远镜
with the largest telescope of his time.
白天  赫歇尔做实验
By day, Herschel performed experiments.
根据牛顿的研究结果  已知日光
From Newton's earlier work, it was known that sunlight
由不同颜色的光混合而成
is a blend of different colors.
所有人都知道  在户外
And everyone knew, just from being outside,
日光带来热量
that sunlight carries heat.
威廉赫歇尔不禁疑问
William Herschel asked
哪种颜色的光带着更多的热量
whether some colors of light carry more heat than others.
科学天才的天性就是对那些
The nature of scientific genius is to question
我们认为理所当然的事情产生疑问
what the rest of us take for granted...
然后做用实验证实
and then do the experiment.
赫歇尔放在光照范围之外的温度计
The thermometer that Herschel placed outside the spectrum
是他的对照物
was his control.
对照物在实验中
The control in any experiment
不参加实验操作
always lacks the factor being tested.
这样才能知道你的实验物
That way, you know if what you're testing is
是否真的是对实验本身产生反应
really the thing responsible for the observation.
在赫歇尔的试验中
In Herschel's experiment,
验证的是
the relationship between
颜色和温度的关系
color and temperature was being tested,
他用一个温度计做对照
and so his control was a thermometer
放在白纸上
over the part of the white sheet
日光照射之外
that was not illuminated by sunlight at all.
那个声音又来了
There's that sound again.
到底是什么
What is that?
红光比蓝光产生更多的热
Okay, red light is warmer than blue light.
有趣的发现 但还不算惊天动地
Interesting discovery, but not exactly revolutionary.
你的温度计没有问题
No, there's nothing wrong with your thermometer.
你只是发现了一种新的光
You've just discovered a new kind of light.
赫歇尔是首位发现在光谱中
Herschel was the first to detect this unseen presence
红色以外或以下 不可见光的人
lurking just below the red end of the spectrum.
这就是红外线名字的由来
That's why it came to be called "infrared."
红外线=infra red
英语的infra在拉丁语中意为 之下
"Infra" is Latin for the word "below."
它不可见
It's invisible.
我们的眼睛对这类光不敏感
Our eyes are not sensitive to this kind of light,
我们的皮肤不同  我们可以感受到热
but our skin is-- we feel it as heat.
这才是真正的重大发现
Now, that's a really big discovery.
但是光线之中依然隐藏着
But far greater secrets were still hiding
更大的秘密
deep inside the light.
几乎与威廉赫歇尔在英格兰
At about the same time that William Herschel
发现红外线的同时
was discovering infrared light in his parlor in England,
一位名叫约瑟夫・夫琅和费的孩子
a young boy named Joseph Fraunhofer
从事着乏味的繁重的工作
was trapped in hopeless drudgery.
他站在盛满有毒化学物的熔炉旁
He stood over a cauldron of toxic chemicals
不断地搅拌
and endlessly stirred.
约瑟夫11岁时成了孤儿
Joseph had been orphaned at the age of 11
被送给苛刻的维塞伯格
and given to a harsh master named Weichselberger,
他替皇家做镜子
the royal mirror-maker.
他不让约瑟夫去上学
He prevented Joseph from going to school.
而是白天让约瑟夫在玻璃作坊做苦力
Instead, Joseph labored in the glass-making workshop by day,
晚上去他家里做家务
and tended to the master's household chores by night.
快点  白痴
Hurry up, stupid!
记住 不许读书
And remember, no reading.
约瑟夫终于解脱了
Until Joseph got his big break.
维塞伯格的房子塌了
Weichselberger's house collapsed.
马克西米利安 巴伐利亚未来的国王
Maximilian, the future king of Bavaria,
急忙来到灾难现场
hurried to the scene of the calamity
向灾民伸出援手
to see if he could help.
马克西米利安出了名的关心他的臣民
Maximilian was known for taking an interest in his subjects,
这在当年并不寻常
which was highly unusual for its time.
在巴伐利亚未来国王的关怀下
In attracting the concern of the future king of Bavaria,
年轻的约瑟夫・夫琅和费
young Joseph Fraunhofer
他的未来从此发生了变化
found an aperture into a different universe.
而且不仅是他个人
And not just for himself.
马克西米利亚王子资助约瑟夫
Prince Maximilian gave Joseph money
并让他的高级顾问
and asked his privy councilor
向这孩子提供更多的帮助
to provide further help to the boy,
提供所需的一切
should it be needed.
维塞伯格还在剥削他
Weichselberger continued to exploit him
不让他去学校
and prevent him from attending school.
但是在王子顾问的干预下
But the prince's councilor intervened,
约瑟夫进入了光学学院
offering Joseph a position at the Optical Institute.
这小小的善举带来了非常丰厚的回报
This small gesture of kindness really paid off.
在他27岁时
By the time he was 27,
约瑟夫・夫琅和费成为了首屈一指的设计师
Joseph Fraunhofer was the world's leading designer
从优质的镜片
of high-quality lenses,
到望远镜和其它光学器材
telescopes and other optical instruments.
他的工厂位于本讷迪克特伯伊昂修道院
His firm was housed here, in the old Benediktbeuren Abbey.
在19世纪上半叶
In the early 19th century,
这可是绝密的 超级的高科技
this was top-secret, ultra-high technology.
早期的本笃会修道士们
The Benedictine monks of earlier times
都要进过保密宣誓
had taken a vow of secrecy.
这种当地的风俗
This local tradition,
加上夫琅和费实验室
and the ability to restrict access
严格的通行制度
to Fraunhofer's laboratory,
让他可以继续掌控
allowed him to maintain control
这些机密
of trade and state secrets.
夫琅和费在实验中使用棱镜
Fraunhofer was experimenting with prisms
来寻找制作精密镜片最佳玻璃
to find the best types of glass for precision lenses.
怎样才能更好的观察
How, he wondered, could he get a better look
棱镜产生的光谱呢
at the spectrum that a prism produced?
弗雷德里希 请把经纬仪拿来
Friedrich, bring me the theodolite, please.
在夫琅和费安装经纬仪的时候
Okay, while Fraunhofer sets up his theodolite--
经纬仪是某种望远镜
it's a kind of telescope--
我带你看看修道院的其它地方
I want to show you something in another part of the abbey.
声波听上去如此动人
Sound waves are so beautiful to hear.
想象一下 会有多迷人如果我们能看到它
Imagine how beautiful they'd be to see.
你想过为什么管风琴的音管长短不一吗
You ever wondered why organ pipes have different lengths?
按下一个琴键
I press a key...
它将一股压缩空气
it sends compressed air
送进特定的管道
into a particular pipe,
产生声波
producing sound waves.
如果我们可以把声波速度降低几百倍
If we could slow the sound waves down a few hundred times,
它看上去就是这样的
they would look like this.
管道的长度
The length of the pipe
决定了可以容纳何种长度的声波
determines the length of the sound wave that can fit inside it.
短的管道发出短的声波
A short pipe gives you a short sound wave.
短的声波产生高的音调或者频率
Short sounds waves have high pitch, or frequency.
我们把声波停下 仔细看看
Let's stop the waves for a better look.
相邻波之间的距离
The distance between adjacent waves
称为 波长
is called the wavelength.
长管道发出长的声波
A long pipe gives you a long sound wave
低音调 或者低频率
with a low pitch, or low frequency.
布兰诗歌 这个中世纪作品的手稿
The medieval manuscript of this music, "Carmina Burana,"
就是在这间修道院发现的
was discovered in this very abbey.
声波无法在真空中传递
Sound waves can't travel through a vacuum.
他们需要传播媒介
They need matter to ride on,
比如空气 水 岩石的分子
like molecules of air, or water, or rock.
但光不需要
But light waves fly solo.
他们可以在太空中穿行
They can move through empty space.
速度很快
And fast--
比声波在空气中快100万倍
a million times faster than sound waves in air.
我们看到的光的波长
And the wavelengths of the light we see
比声波的要短得多
are so much shorter than sound waves.
5万个光波
About 50,000 light waves
就这么长
would fit right in here.
对了
Oh, yeah.
夫琅和费
Fraunhofer.
时间正好
Just in time.
正好赶上
We didn't miss it.
就如同声音的波长
Just as the wavelength of sound
决定我们听到的音调
determines the pitch that we hear,
光的波长
the wavelength of light
决定了我们看到的颜色
determines the color that we see.
棱镜是如何将颜色
But how does a prism spread out the colors
从一束日光中分开的呢
concealed in a beam of sunlight?
当光穿过空气或太空
When light travels through air or space,
所有的颜色速度保持一致
all its colors move at the same speed.
但当它以一个角度照射到玻璃上时
But when it hits glass at an angle,
光慢下来 并改变了方向
the light slows down and changes direction.
在棱镜内
Inside the prism,
不同的颜色以不用的速度移动
each color moves at a different speed.
在玻璃中  蓝紫色
In glass, violet light,
由我们看到的最短的光波产生
which is carried by the shortest waves we see,
速度比红光还慢
slows down more than red light,
红光的光波最长
which has the longest waves.
速度的改变
These changes in speed
将不同颜色分开
pry the colors apart,
把他们的光波发散到
sending their waves off
稍微不同的方向
in slightly different directions.
这就是棱镜的原理
That's how a prism works.
如果我等会情绪失控
If I seem unduly emotional about this,
都是因为约瑟夫・夫琅和费将要做的
it's because Joseph Fraunhofer is about to do
是牛顿可以做 却没有做的
what Isaac Newton could've done, but didn't.
它将带来深远的影响
And it'll have a powerful effect
对我自身来说
on the course of my own life.
你见证的是
You are witnessing the marriage
物理学和天文学的结合
of physics and astronomy,
我研究的这个领域的诞生
the birth of my own field of science,
天体物理学
astrophysics.
记录在光线中
Written in the light,
在那些垂直的黑线中的
in those vertical black lines...
是神秘的密码
is secret code.
夫琅和费看着它们 自忖道
Fraunhofer looked at them, and wondered...
为什么
Why?
从外层空间传来的密码
A code that comes to us from an alien universe.
这些黑色的竖线包含怎样的信息呢
What is the message written in these dark, vertical lines?
人们花费了上百年去思考
It took a hundred years of thinking,
探询和调查去破译
questioning, searching to decipher it.
很妙吧
Lovely, isn't it?
为什么
Why?
美丽的精细结构由许多层次组成
There are many layers to the fine structure of beauty...
地球的化学成分 和它的大气层
the chemistry of the Earth and its atmosphere...
生命的进化
the evolution of life...
独特的脉络
Many distinct threads.
我们就在表面挑一个观察
Let's just examine one, at the surface...
令我们惊叹的大自然的颜色
the colors of nature that dazzle us.
到底是什么
What's really happening?
这些红色 蓝色
How does the red, the blue...
简直就是大自然的神奇调色盘
the astonishing palette of nature's colors...
怎么产生的
how do they happen?
太阳发出不同长度的光波
Light waves of different lengths from the Sun
射到地球
strike the Earth.
这些花的花瓣
The petals of these particular flowers
吸收所有低能量的
absorb all the low-energy,
长的红色光波
long red wavelengths of light.
但是花瓣反射
But the petals reflect
短的 高能量的 蓝色光波
the shorter, high-energy blue wavelengths.
星光与花瓣之间的这种互动
That interaction between starlight and petal--
还有水 还有梵高
or water, or Van Gogh--
使之产生了蓝色
is what makes blue.
最长的光波
The longest waves,
我们所看到的红色
the ones we see as red,
有着最低的能量
have the lowest energy.
颜色是我们的眼睛
Color is the way our eyes perceive
分辨光波能量的方式
how energetic light waves are.
日落
A sunset...
旗帜
a flag...
情人的眼睛
the eyes of your beloved...
闪亮的新车
that shiny new car.
他们带来的灵感
The feelings they inspire
激发你内在的某些东西
happen when something inside you
由一种特殊的变化产生
is triggered by a particular variation
光波的能量与频率的变化
in the frequency and energy of light waves.
神秘的信息
And the secret message?
那些黑色竖线
Those black vertical lines
夫琅和费在光谱中看到的
in Fraunhofer's spectrum?
他们怎么产生的
What makes them?
他们产生于 某些特定颜色
They occur when the light waves
的光波被吸收时
of those particular colors are being absorbed.
那是发生在另一个层面的事情
It happens on another level of reality,
比我们身处的这个世界小的多得多
far smaller than the world we're used to operating in.
要去那里 我们必须变得
To get there, we'll need to become
比现在小100亿倍
ten billion times smaller than we are.
我们可以从这些原子中任选一个
We could pick any one of these atoms.
还是选氢原子吧
But let's go for the hydrogen atom.
氢原子是宇宙中
The hydrogen atom is the most plentiful kind
最普遍的一种
of atom in the cosmos.
最简单的
And the simplest.
只有一个电子
It has only one electron.
只有一个质子
And only one proton.
我们进入了量子领域
We've entered the quantum realm.
这并不符合
It doesn't correspond
通常的经验
to ordinary human experience.
常识在这里不起作用
Common sense is no help here at all.
以氢原子的电子为例
Take the hydrogen atom's electron, for example.
在原子中 电子
In an atom, an electron
并不存在于轨道之间
doesn't exist between orbitals.
它从一个轨道消失
It disappears from one orbital
又在另一个轨道出现
and reappears in another.
就像你坐电梯从2楼去4楼
It's as if you took an elevator from the second floor to the fourth floor,
却凭空消失
but ceased to exist in between.
还有
And another thing.
量子电梯并不会停在特定的楼层
Quantum elevators only stop at certain floors.
电子的轨道尺寸有着严格的限制
The sizes of the electron orbits are strictly limited,
每种元素的原子都不相同
and different for the atoms of every element.
这就是元素各不相同的原因
That's why the elements are different.
所有物质的化学属性都由它的电子的轨道决定
The chemistry of anything is determined by its electron orbits.
将电子束缚在轨道上的力量
The force that holds an electron in orbit
和重力没有丝毫关系
has nothing to do with gravity.
它是电气引力
It's a force of electrical attraction.
电子沿着波浪形的圆环
The electron dances a wavy ring
环绕氢原子的原子核运行
around the central nucleus of a hydrogen atom.
从一个轨道跳到另一个轨道
And makes quantum leaps from orbit to orbit.
忽上忽下
Up or down.
轨道越大
The larger the orbit,
电子的能量越大
the greater the energy of an electron.
电子必须获取能量才能跳跃到更大的轨道上
An electron has to get energy to leap to a larger orbit.
然后必须释放能量才能跳回来
And it has to lose energy to jump back down.
每次向上的跳跃都是原子吸收光波的结果
Every upward leap is caused by... an atom absorbing a light wave.
我们还不知道是什么使它向下跳跃
But we have no idea what causes the downward leaps.
我们只知道向下跳跃产生光波
What we do know that such leaps always produce a light wave
这种光波的颜色与轨道间的能量差异相吻合
whose color matches the energy difference between the orbitals.
太阳的表面辐射出所有颜色的光波
The Sun's surface radiates light waves of all colors.
如果你透过棱镜看日光
If you look at sunlight through a prism,
你能看到它的光谱
you'll see its spectrum.
当你用望远镜放大光谱时
When you magnify the spectrum with a telescope,
就像约瑟夫・夫琅和费那样
as Joseph Fraunhofer did,
你就可以窥视
you raise the curtain
电子在原子中跳跃的真相
on the electron dance within the atom.
当电子的能量衰弱
When the energy of the electron flags,
它降到较低的轨道时
and it drops to a lower orbital,
光波逸散
the light wave it emits scatters.
大多数不会到我们这里
Most of it doesn't reach us.
这就留下了一个黑暗的空当
That leaves a dark gap
或者说 光谱中的黑色竖线
or black vertical line in the spectrum.
这些黑线就是
These dark lines are the shadows
氢原子在太阳大气层中造成的阴影
cast by hydrogen atoms in the atmosphere of the Sun.
钠原子发出不同的阴影
Sodium atoms cast different shadows.
他们的电子按照不同的曲子跳舞
Their electrons dance to a different tune.
一粒盐由钠原子和氯原子组成
A grain of table salt is composed of sodium and chlorine atoms.
千万亿的原子疯狂地舞动
Ten million billion of them doing their crazy dances
仅仅是在一粒盐中
in a single grain of salt.
一个铁原子有26个电子
And a single iron atom with 26 electrons
庞大的宛如百老汇音乐剧的制作团队
is like a great big production number in a Broadway musical.
当你用分光仪观察星星时
When you look at a star with a spectroscope,
在它大气层中所有元素上都能看到黑线
you see the dark lines from all the elements in its atmosphere.
给我任意一个物体的光谱
Show me the spectrum of anything,
不论是在地球上的 还是在遥远的星星上
whether here on Earth or from a distant star,
我都可以告诉你 它的元素构成
and I'll tell you what it's made of.
夫琅和费线是元素的原子签名
Fraunhofer's lines are the atomic signatures
遍布整个宇宙
of the elements writ large across the cosmos.
如同科学历史上的
As with every other major revelation
其它重大发现一样  它带来了
in the history of science, it opened the way
更新更深层次的谜团
to newer and deeper mysteries.
还有更多地
And to the revelation that there were
秘密依然藏在光线中
many more secrets hiding in the light.
当夫琅和费把望远镜和棱镜结合在一起
When Joseph Fraunhofer combined a prism with a telescope
用它们探索天空
and turned it toward the skies,
他将星星与我们之间的距离缩短了
he brought the stars much closer to us.
他39岁时
When he was only 39,
他身患重病
he contracted a fatal illness.
可能是由于早年长期曝露在
Perhaps as a result of his early and long-term exposure
制作玻璃的有毒化学物质的缘故
to the toxic chemicals of glassmaking.
你永远不知道下一个天才在何处诞生
You never know where the next genius will come from.
不知道我们错过了多少天才
How many of them do we leave in the rubble?
对一位孤儿的善行给王子
The prince and his kingdom were immeasurably enriched
和他的王国带来不可计量的财富
by that act of kindness to a poor orphan.
夫琅和费的发现将巴伐利亚
Fraunhofer's discoveries transformed Bavaria
从偏僻的乡下变成高科技的制造中心
from a rural backwater to a technological powerhouse.
在他弥留之际  政府急切地
As he lay dying, the government was desperate
想要保留他所有的关于
to preserve every shred of his precious knowledge
高科技光学玻璃的宝贵知识
about the high technology of optical glass.
但这只能让一个人知道
But it could only be divulged to a person
此人有着最高级别的涉密权限
with top security clearance--
铸币局主管
the director of the mint.
政府保留了夫琅和费的技术
The government kept Fraunhofer's technology
用于制造完美的光学玻璃
for making perfect optical glass
一个上百年的国家机密
a State secret for another hundred years.
后来证明这给某人带来很大的阻碍
This would prove to be a major obstacle
以后我们会提到
for someone we'll meet later in our journey.
但夫琅和费不能容忍这样
But Fraunhofer would allow no such secrecy
对他的科学研究保密
where his pure scientific research was concerned.
他知道科学需要开放才能昌盛
He knew that science requires openness to flourish;
我们对于自然地了解属于全世界
that our understanding of nature belongs to the world.
夫琅和费发现谱线后
As soon as Fraunhofer discovered the spectral lines,
他立即发表了所有的成果
he published everything he knew about them.
如此重要的发现带来的影响
And the reverberations of his momentous discovery
持续至今
echo still.
他的谱线揭示了可观测宇宙
His spectral lines revealed that the visible cosmos
是由相同的元素构成
is all made of the same elements.
行星们
The planets...
恒星们
The stars...
星系们
The galaxies...
我们  还有所有的生命体
We, ourselves, and all of life...
拥有共同的物质
The same star stuff.
他让我们知道了
He made it possible for us to know
其它星球的大气层中有些什么
what's in the atmosphere of other worlds.
远在上百万光年外的星系中
And in galaxies millions of light-years away.
谱线不止揭示了遥远物体的成分
Spectral lines revealed not only the composition
也揭示了他们是在靠近还是远离我们
of far-off objects, but also their motion towards or away from us.
通过它 我们发现我们的宇宙还在扩张
Using them, we discovered that our universe is expanding.
但分光仪最伟大的作用
But perhaps the greatest revelation of spectroscopy
是发现了不可见光
is the discovery of the thing it cannot see.
暗物质的隐蔽宇宙
A hidden universe of dark matter
质量比我们熟悉的宇宙超出6倍
six times more massive than the familiar cosmos.
由某些神秘的物质组成
It's made of some mysterious substance
不会发出 反射或者吸收任何形式的光
that does not emit, reflect or absorb any kind of light.
因为它的引力我们才知道它的存在
We only know it's there because of its gravity,
它的引力吸引着星系
which pulls on all the galaxies
并为其中的恒星加速
and speeds up the visible stars within them.
我们的眼睛可以看见很多种类的光
There are many more kinds of light than our eyes can see.
认为我们的自然只有可见光
Confining our perception of nature to visible light
就如同听的音乐
is like listening to music
只有一个八度
in only one octave.
其实还有很多很多
There are so many more.
他们仅仅是波长的区别
They differ only in wavelength,
只是范围很大
but over a huge range.
比如 红外线
For instance, infrared light...
威廉费歇尔发现的那种
the kind that William Herschel discovered
X光
Or X-ray light.
无线电波
Or radio light.
伽马射线
Or in gamma-ray light.
不仅是看东西的方式不同
These are not just different ways of seeing the same thing.
不同的光
These other kinds of light
揭示出宇宙中不同的物体和现象
reveal different objects and phenomena in the cosmos.
比方说通过伽马射线 它使我们可以
In gamma-ray light, for example, we can see mysterious explosions
不再错过
in distant galaxies
遥远星系的神秘爆炸
that we would otherwise miss.
通过微波 我们可以看到
And in microwave light, we can see all the way back
宇宙诞生之初的情景
to the birth of the universe.
我们只不过才刚刚开始睁开眼睛
We have only just opened our eyes.